If you were European in the 16th century you thought the earth was lying in the middle of the universe-
-And for the most part was country - at least to 70 %.
An almost dry plane, where the Atlantic was more like a pool of water.
But over the next centuries, your worldview changes totally.
The exciting with early modern time-
-Is that everything people in Europe think they know is put to an end.
In the early modern period, man understands for the first time-
-How she looks inside and that there are more than three continents-
-And share shocking ideas like that all people have reason.
What do all discoveries get for consequences-
-For Europe's development and people?
Europe's early history can be divided into three eras.
This is the last and shortest: early modern time.
We used to be divided into the Renaissance and enlightenment.
It begins when Columbus lands on an unknown continent-
For a Western Gothic farmer- how was the difference between the 16th and 18th centuries?
The sad answer is that it might not be such a big difference.
For the farmer it may not be that-
-But the 14th-century Italian humanist-
-Iri that it is a significant difference.
They see a rebirth of antiquity arts and sciences-
-But it is also the time of discovery.
You are out at sea.
This is how trade and cultural exchange takes place.
You have to have a compass, and this is a rosecap pass.
The magnet is drawn against the earth's magnetic north pole.
One who has one of those is Christofer Columbus-
-He whose journey is so important that it marks the start of the era.
The goal is to find a new sea route to India.
After a few months at sea, he reaches land on October 12, 1492.
He thinks he came to Asia and is looking for proof of that.
One begins to realize that the image like the Old Testament, the Bible and the Church Ger-
-Not not matching reality.
Can the Bible, who for almost a thousand years have had the answer to all questions, be wrong?
The new continent leads to a revolution in science.
People are starting to investigate, with the goal of learning more about their surroundings.
The scientific revolution involves both discoveries-
-and a new way to discover the world.
A way to examine the nature-
-To draw conclusions about what is true and how nature works.
Those conclusions can be spread in a new way-
-With Gutenberg's invention.
Now you can buy your own copy and have it at home in your car.
In a book, Copernicus questions that the earth is the center of the universe.
It is picked up by Galileo Galilei, who for his help has one like this.
The binoculars came in the 17th century.
The longing it is, the greater the magnification.
Galilei's telescope directed toward space gave three times magnifying-
-But already next year he received 33 times magnification.
One night he directs it toward space, and in 33 times enlarg-
-He is something that no one has seen before.
Now he can confirm that Copernicus was right.
The earth is not the center of the universe.
The legs should not make any decisions.
The head should do that.
The metaphor shows to the people that everyone has their place.
The early modern society is obsessed with hierarchies and rank.
You know your place.
If you are a nobleman you must have certain clothes that citizens must not have.
One should look directly at a nobleman that the person in question is noble.
Rich people can buy themselves free from sin and get a simple path to heaven.
It is also being questioned within the church.
Here the monk Martin Luther nails 95 points at the church in Wittenberg.
They change the church and Europe for all time.
Luther believes that someone may be right against the pope and church-
-If they have support from the Bible.
"Slowly on the slopes," the Pope says, threatening with banning.
Luther sets fire to the letter, and then it goes fast.
The dissatisfaction spreads like a wildfeld
-And the Roman Catholic Church split.
Luther's criticism of the church becomes a kind of catalyzer-
-for a lot of dissatisfaction lying and putting in Europe-
-Both politically and religiously.
Kings and princes see their chance.
If they join Luther and carry out a Reformation-
-Can they free themselves from the Catholic Church and strengthen their power.
One who takes the chance is Gustav Vasa.
"We're going to be there too."
Gustav II Adolf and the army close up with the Protestant princes.
The king falls, but Sweden ends up on the winning side with France-
-When the Westphalian Peace closed
Sweden is now the big player that others must relate to.
Sweden has a large army, and you do not want to happen to it.
You don't want to.
In the footsteps of the war we see plundered villages and trampled arable land.
In some areas, the number of inhabitants drops by a quarter.
Westphalian peace changes the balance of power.
The Habsburg Emperor Empire is weakened, especially in Germany.
Sweden builds an empire-
-But at the top of the podium steps France.
France becomes a host nation for the new philosophers of the new age.
Here's ideas about nature, science and not least man.
The 18th century is called the century of reason.
There is enormous optimism about human reason.
There is nothing she cannot do with her reason.
Now one thinks that everyone has a reason-
-To and with at the bottom of the hierarchy - the legs in the illustration.
In many countries there will be censorship.
Some that are discussed are about how a country should be governed.
Sweden has a slightly different development.
Hair prevails
-When almost is a political experiment with a weak royal power.
It gives us the Freedom of Pressure Regulation, a constitution that we still have today.
When the Riksdag 1766 faces freedom of the press, you do it as a response-
-On the requirement that you want to be able to write and print anything.
Religious writings are exempt.
They are not allowed to speak freely om-
-But for political criticism it is free.
The time of freedom ends drastically with Gustav III's coup 1772.
But how should a state be ruled if we can decide?
The enlightenment philosophers have three ways.
Montesquieu presents a power distribution principle-
-with a legislative, a judgment and an executive power.
-And in France the people take power and dismiss their king.
The early modern time begins to pass into modern times-
-When we get revolutions that think this is wrong.
Power should be divided into the entire population.
How is the rest of the world affected by the early modern time?
The contact between America's indigenous people and Europeans-
-As probably the biggest disaster in the last thousand years.
The discovery trips and colonization that began to era-
-In crucial for the future of Europe and the rest of the world.
From the colonies, trade is conducted that only benefits European states.
To motivate resources, you develop ideologies.
That one is better racially and religiously legitimizes extinction-
-Or that you slaughter the people there brutal ways.
The most economically important is the establishment of plantation economies-
-In the Caribbean, North America and South America.
They demanded slave labor.
Now you are picking slaves, and it has fateful consequences.
In the transatlantic triangle trade, boats move in a triangle.
Europe receives raw materials from America with enslaved labor from Africa.
That fine view of man with the right to his life-
-Do not effect everyone.
There is perhaps an idea that one belongs to a civilization-
-As is higher than these cultures and peoples.
Colonization gives us an influence on other continents that are unique.
We will never have the same influence on the outside world as during this time.
Many of the thoughts, ideas and discoveries of this time are still alive today.
The tracks we can see today include
our tax system and secularisation-
-But above all, our modern states develop over an early modern time.
Swedish texture: Per Lundgren Iyuno-Di Group for UR